I thought I would read poems I have that relate to the subject
أعتقد أني أريد أن اقراء قصيده تعود الى موضوع
of youth and age.
عن الحديث والقديم .
I was sort of astonished to find out how many I have actually.
كان لدي شيئا من الاندهاش لمعرفة الكم كم منها لدي فعلا .
The first one is dedicated to
القصيده الآولى كانت مكرسة
Spencer, and his grandmother, who was shocked by his work.
ل سبينسر , وجدته ,التي اصيبت بالدهشة من عمله .
My poem is called "Dirt."
قصيدتي اسمها "الوسخ"
My grandmother is washing my mouth out with soap;
جدتي تغسل فمي بالصابون :
half a long century gone
على طول نصف قرن مضى
and still she comes at me
ولازالت تأتي الي
with that thick cruel yellow bar.
مع هذا الشريط الآصفر القاسي
All because of a word I said,
كل هذا بسبب كلمة قلتها ,
not even said really, only repeated.
لا بل الحقيقه , ليست سوى تكرار.
But "Open," she says, "open up!"
لكن "أفتح ,"قالت هي ,"فتح !"
her hand clawing at my head.
تخمش يدها على راسي .
I know now her life was hard;
أعرف أن حياتها كانت صعبه :
she lost three children as babies,
خسرت ثلاث أطفال رضع ,
then her husband died too,
ثم توفي زوجها أيضا ,
leaving young sons, and no money.
ترك أبناء ,وليس مالا .
She'd stand me in the sink to pee
كانت تقف أمامي لآتبول
because there was never room in the toilet.
لانه لم يكن هناك متسع لمرحاض .
But oh, her soap!
لكن اه ,صابونتها !
Might its bitter burning have been
ربما كان حرقا مريرا
what made me a poet?
مالذي جعلني شاعرا ؟
The street she lived on was unpaved,
الطريق الذي عاشته لم يكن ممهدا
her flat, two cramped rooms and a fetid kitchen
شقتها ,غرفتين ضيقتين ومطبخ نتن
where she stalked and caught me.
في المكان الذي لاحقتني فيه وأمسكتني .
Dare I admit that after she did it
أجروء على الآعتراف بعد أن فعلت ذلك
I never really loved her again?
أني لم أعد أحبها ثانية ؟
She lived to a hundred,
عاشت حتى المئة
even then. All along it was the sadness, the squalor,
حتى ذلك الحين . على طول تلك الفترة كان الحزن, والقذارة,
but I never, until now
لكن ابدا , حتى الآن
loved her again.
لم أحبها مرة أخرى .
When that was published in a magazine
عندما نشر هذا في الجريدة
I got an irate letter from my uncle.
تلقيت رساله غاضبه من عمي .
"You have maligned a great woman."
"أنت تعيب أمراءة عظيمه ."
It took some diplomacy.
أحتاج الآمر بعض الدبلوماسية .
This is called "The Dress."
يسمى هذا "اللباس."
It's a longer poem.
أنها قصيدة طويلة .
In those days,
في تلك الآيام ,
those days which exist for me only
تلك الايام التي وجدت لي وحدي
as the most elusive memory now,
أنها بعيدة المنال عن الذاكرة
when often the first sound you'd hear in the morning
التي في كثير من الآحيان الصوت الآول الذي تسمعه في الصباح
would be a storm of birdsong,
يبدوا وكأنه عاصفة من تغريد العصافير ,
then the soft clop of the hooves
ثم طرق ناعم للحوافر
of the horse hauling a milk wagon down your block,
للحصان يشد عربة الحليب بعيدا عن حظيرتك ,
and the last sound at night as likely as not
والصوت الآخير في الليل لايشبه هذا
would be your father pulling up in his car,
سيكون والدك وهو يجر في سيارته ,
having worked late again, always late,
لديه عمل متأخر مرة أخرى ,دائما متأخر ,
and going heavily down to the cellar, to the furnace,
وتذهب بتثاقل الى القبو , الى الفرن .
to shake out the ashes and damp the draft
لتهز الرماد وترطب الجو
before he came upstairs to fall into bed --
قبل أن يصعد الطابق العلوي لينسل في سريره--
in those long-ago days,
في هذه الايام في زمن بعيد
women, my mother, my friends' mothers,
النساء , أمي , أمهات أصدقائي ,
our neighbors, all the women I knew --
جاراتنا , جميع النساء الذين عرفتهم --
wore, often much of the day,
يرتدين , في معظم اليوم ,
what were called housedresses,
ماكان يسمى ملابس منزلية ,
cheap, printed, pulpy,
رخيصة , مطبوعة , وسميكة ,
seemingly purposefully shapeless
على مايبدو تعمد جعلها بشعة
light cotton shifts that you wore over your nightgown
القطن الخفيف المتحول الذي ترتدونه في ملابس النوم
and, when you had to go look for a child,
و , عندما تذهب للبحث على طفل ,
hang wash on the line,
شنقا يغسل على الخط ,
or run down to the grocery store on the corner,
أو النزول مسرعا الى البقالة في الزاوية ,
under a coat,
تحت السترة ,
the twisted hem of the nightgown
والتنحنح الملتوي لملابس النوم
always lank and yellowed,
دائما باهت وأصفر ,
dangling beneath.
تتدلى أسفلها .
More than the curlers some of the women
أكثر من نص النساء بكروا عن البعض الاخر
seemed constantly to have in their hair
بدوا يستمرون في شكل شعورهم
in preparation for some great event --
في التجهيز لحدث عظيم--
a ball, one would think --
كرة ,أحدهم سوف يفكر --
that never came to pass;
أنها لن ترى النور ابدا :
more than the way most women's faces
معظم الطريق أغلب وجوه النساء
not only were never made up during the day,
لم تكن ابدا تتكون خلال اليوم ,
but seemed scraped, bleached,
لكن يبدوا مكشوطا , ومبيضا ,
and, with their plucked eyebrows, scarily masklike;
و , مع حواجبهم الملتقطه ,يشبة القناع المخيف
more than all that it was those dresses
والاكثر من هذا كان كل هذه الملابس
that made women so unknowable and forbidding,
الذي جعل النساء غير معروفات ومحرمات ,
adepts of enigmas to which men could have no access,
أتباع اللالغاز التي لايمكن للرجل الوصول اليها ,
and boys no conception.
واي تصور للاولاد .
Only later would I see the dresses also
فقط لاحقا أريد أن ارى هذه الملابس أيضا
as a proclamation:
كأعلان :
that in your dim kitchen, your laundry,
في مطبخك المعتم ,في مغسلتك ,
your bleak concrete yard,
فناءك الكئيب ,
what you revealed of yourself
الذي تكشف فيه عن نفسك
was a fabulation;
كانت مسرحية :
your real sensual nature,
حقيقة طبيعتك الحساسة ,
veiled in those sexless vestments,
مختفية في هذه الاثواب الضعيفة جنسيا ,
was utterly your dominion.
كان تماما في سلطتك .
In those days, one hid much else as well:
في هذه الايام ,يخفي الناس بقدر مايستطيعون :
grown men didn't embrace one another,
الرجال الناضجون لايحرج احدهم الاخر ,
unless someone had died,
الا شخص واحد مات ,
and not always then; you shook hands
وليس دائما : يجب أن تصافح
or, at a ball game, thumped your friend's back
أو , كام في لعبة الكرة ,تسحق مؤخرة صديقك
and exchanged blows meant to be codes for affection;
وللتبادل الضربات لتكون رموز للعاطفة :
once out of childhood you'd never again know
مرة في الطفولة لك تعد تعرفها ابدا
the shock of your father's whiskers on your cheek,
أن تهز سالف والدك في خدودك ,
not until mores at last had evolved,
ليست اكثر من أعراف على الاقل قد تطورت ,
and you could hug another man, then hold on for a moment,
وتسطتيع أن تعانق رجل اخر , ثم توقف للحظه,
then even kiss (your fathers bristles
ثم حتى القبلة لشعيرات والدك
white and stiff now).
بيضاء وقاسية الان .
What release finally, the embrace:
الذي أطلق اخيرا , العناق :
though we were wary -- it seemed so audacious --
رغم ذلك كنا حذرين --يبدو هذا جريء جدا --
how much unspoken joy there was
كم من المرح غير المعلن يوجد
in that affirmation of equality and communion,
في هذا الاثبات للمساواة والتواصل ,
no matter how much misunderstanding
لايهم كم هو سوء الفهم
and pain had passed between you by then.
والالم التي قد مرت بك بعد ذلك الحين
We knew so little in those days,
نحننعلم القليل في هذه الآيام ,
as little as now, I suppose
كما هو الحال الان , أعتقد
about healing those hurts:
لمداواة هذه الجروح :
even the women, in their best dresses,
حتى النساء, في أفضل حلتهم ,
with beads and sequins sewn on the bodices,
مع الخرز والترتر المخيط على الاجساد ,
even in lipstick and mascara,
حتى في أحمر الشفاه والماسكارا ,
their hair aflow,
في شعرهم المنسدل ,
could only stand wringing their hands,
يستطيعون الوقوف فقط وفرك أيديهم ,
begging for peace,
راجيين السلام ,
while father and son, like thugs,
في أثناء وقوف الآبناء وألاباء , كالبلطجيه ,
like thieves, like Romans,
كاللصوص,كالرومان ,
simmered and hissed and hated,
يجيش ويهسهس ويكره ,
inflicting sorrows that endured,
تلحق الندم في هذا التحمل
the worst anyway,
الاسواء على كل حال ,
through the kiss and embrace,
خلال القبل والعناق ,
bleeding from brother to brother,
يتدفق من أخ لآخ و
into the generations.
الى الآجيال .
In those days there was still countryside
في تلك الآيام كان مايزال الريف موجودا
close to the city, farms, cornfields, cows;
قريبا من المدينة , المزارع ,حقول الذرة, الابقار :
even not far from our building
حتى أنه لك بعيدا عن أبنيتنا
with its blurred brick and long shadowy hallway
مع الطوب الواضح وأروقته الطويلة المظلمة
you could find tracts with hills and trees
يمكن أن تجد مسارك في التلال والآشجار
you could pretend were mountains and forests.
يمكن أن تتدعي وجود جبال وغابات
Or you could go out by yourself
أو يمكنك الذهاب بنفسك
even to a half-block-long empty lot,
حتى لنصف مسافة طويلة جرداء ,
into the bushes: like a creature of leaves you'd lurk,
الى الشجيرات :كالمخلوق من النباتات كنت كامنا ,
crouched, crawling, simplified, savage, alone;
جاثم, يزحف,بسيط , وحشي , وحيد :
already there was wanting to be simpler,
بالفعل كان هناك يريد أن يكون ابسط ,
wanting, when they called you,
يريدونك , عندما ينادونك ,
never to go back.
لن تعود ابدا .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is another longish one,
هذا واحد اخر طويل قليللا ,
about the old and the young.
عن القديم والحديث .
It actually happened right at the time we met.
حدث فعلا بالوقت الذي تقابلنا فيه
Part of the poem takes place in
جزء من القصيده قيل في
space we shared and time we shared.
الوقت والمساحه الذين تقاسمناهما
It's called "The Neighbor."
تسمى "الجار"
Her five horrid, deformed little dogs
كلابها الصغار الخمسه , القاسون
who incessantly yap on the roof under my window.
الذين يحلون ياب على الروف تحت شباكي .
Her cats, God knows how many,
هررها , الله وحده يعلم كم عددهم ,
who must piss on her rugs --
الذين يجب أن يتبولوا على سجادتها ,
her landing's a sickening reek.
أرضها تفوح منها رائحة مقززة .
Her shadow once, fumbling the chain on her door,
فجأة ظلها , يتحسس السلسلة على على بابها ,
then the door slamming fearfully shut,
ثم الباب يغلق بهجوم مخيف ,
only the barking and the music -- jazz --
فقط العواء والموسيقى -- الجاز --
filtering as it does, day and night into the hall.
يتسلل كما يفعل , ليل نهار الى الردهة.
The time it was Chris Connor singing "Lush Life" --
في هذه الاثناء كان كريس كونر يغني "سوط الحياة "
how it brought back my college sweetheart,
كيف عدت الى جامعتي حبيبتي ,
my first real love, who -- till I left her --
حبي الاول الحقيقي , من -- حتى تركتها --
played the same record.
أعدت تشغيل نفس المسجل .
And head on my shoulder, hand on my thigh,
وراسي على كتفي ,ويدي على فخذي ,
sang sweetly along, of regrets and depletions
غنى بعذوبة طويلا, عن الندم لاستنفاد الفرص
she was too young for,
كانت فتية جدا لهذا ,
as I was too young, later, to believe in her pain.
كما اني كنت فتيا جدا , لاحقا , لتصدق المها
It startled, then bored, then repelled me.
وذهلت ,وملت , ثم صدتني .
My starting to fancy she'd ended up in this fire-trap
بداية نزوتي كانت قد انتهت هي في فخ هذا الحريق
in the Village, that my neighbor was her.
في القرية , هذه الجارة كانت هي .
My thinking we'd meet, recognize one another,
تفكيري الذي تقابلنا به ,نتعرف به على بعضنا ,
become friends, that I'd accomplish a penance.
أصبحنا أصدقاء , قد أستطعت تحقيق التكفير عن الذنب .
My seeing her, it wasn't her, at the mailbox.
نظرت اليها , لم تكن هي , في علبة .
Gray-yellow hair, army pants under a nightgown,
شعرها الرمادي الاصفر ,سراويل الجيش تحت ملابس النوم ,
her turning away, hiding her ravaged face
لها الابتعاد ,تخبئ وجهها المشوه
in her hands, muttering an inappropriate "Hi."
في يديها ,دندنة "بمرحبا" غير لائقة
Sometimes there are frightening goings-on in the stairwell.
في بعض الآحيان توج خائفة ممايحدث على الدرج .
A man shouting, "Shut up!" The dogs frantically snarling,
رجل يصرخ , " أخرس !"الكلاب محمومة بالزمجرة ,
claws scrabbling, then her -- her voice
مخالب يحفرون , ثم هي -- صوتها
hoarse, harsh, hollow,
فظ , قاسي , أجوف ,
almost only a tone,
بالكاد لهجة فقط ,
incoherent, a note, a squawk,
غير مترابطة , مذكرة ,قهقهة ,
bone on metal, metal gone molten,
عظام على الحديد , والحديد ينصهر ,
calling them back,
يدعوهم للعودة ,
"Come back darlings, come back dear ones.
" عودي ياعزيزتي , عودي ياأعز شخص .
My sweet angels, come back."
ملاكي الحلو , عودي "
Medea she was, next time I saw her.
كانت كالمدية , مرة اخرى رايتها .
Sorceress, tranced, ecstatic,
ساحرة ,فاتنة ,منتشية ,
stock-still on the sidewalk
مازالت تمشي بغطرسة على الرصيف
ragged coat hanging agape,
شنقت باندهاش بسترة ممزقه ,
passersby flowing around her,
المارة يتدفقون من حولها ,
her mouth torn suddenly open
فمها الممزق فتح فجائة
as though in a scream,
كما لو أنها تصرخ,
silently though, as though only in her brain
بالرغم من صمتها , كما لو أنه الوحيد في عقلها
or breast had it erupted.
أو صدورنا كانت قد اشتعلت .
A cry so pure, practiced, detached,
حتى بكاءها نقي ,ممارس , منفصل ,
it had no need of a voice,
لم يكن محتاج لصوت ,
or could no longer bear one.
أو لم يعد يستطيع تحمل وحده .
These invisible links that allure,
تجذبة هذه الروابط الخفية ,
these transfigurations, even of anguish, that hold us.
الذي يجعلنا كذلك .تبدل الهيئة هذا , حتى الاسى .
The girl, my old love,
الفتاة ,حبي القديم ,
the last lost time I saw her
في ماضي الوقت الضائع رأيتها
when she came to find me at a party,
عندما أتت لتجدني في حفلة ,
her drunkenly stumbling, falling,
تعثرت بثملها , وقعت ,
sprawling, skirt hiked, eyes veined red,
ترامت ,ارتفعت تنورتها , عيونها حمراء ,
swollen with tears, her shame,
متورمة بالدمع ,عارها ,
her dishonor.
فقدانها لشرفها
My ignorant, arrogant coarseness,
تجاهلي , تغطرسي الفظ ,
my secret pride, my turning away.
اعتزازي السري , ابتعادي .
Still life on a rooftop,
تبقى الحياة على السطح ,
dead trees in barrels, a bench broken,
الاشجار الميتة في برميل , مقعد مكسر ,
dogs, excrement, sky.
براز الكلاب , السماء .
What pathways through pain,
ماهي المسارات من خلال الالم ,
what junctures of vulnerability,
ماهي منعطفات الضعف ,
what crossings and counterings?
ماهو العابر وماهو المتصدي ؟
Too many lives in our lives already,
أرواح كثيرة في حياتنا فعلا ,
too many chances for sorrow,
كثير من الفرص للندم ,
too many unaccounted-for pasts.
كثيرون من مجهولي المصير للماضي .
"Behold me," the god of frenzied,
"ها لي ,"الاله المسعور ,
inexhaustible love says,
الحب لايتعب يقولون ,
rising in bloody splendor, "Behold me."
يرتفع برونقه الدموي , "ها لي "
Her making her way
صنعها لطريقها
down the littered vestibule stairs,
اسفل الدرج تناثر الدهليز
one agonized step at a time.
تعذبت في خطوة واحده في وقت واحد .
My holding the door.
عقدي للباب .
Her crossing the fragmented tiles,
عبورها بلاط مبعثر,
faltering at the step to the street,
تعثرت في خطواتها الى الطريق ,
droning, not looking at me,
متكاسلة , لاتنظر في وجهي ,
"Can you help me?"
" هل تستطيع مساعدتي ؟"
Taking my arm, leaning lightly against me.
أخذت بيدي , تميل قليلا ضدي .
Her wavering step into the world.
خطواتها المتعرجه للعالم .
Her whispering, "Thanks love." Lightly, lightly against me.
يهمس لها ,"شكرا ايها الحب ."قليلا ,قليلا ضدي .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
I think I'll lighten up a little.
أعتقد أني سأخفف قليلا .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Another, different kind of poem of youth and age.
نوع اخر , تختلف عن نوع قصائد القديم والحديث .
It's called "Gas."
أسميتها "رِيح "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Wouldn't it be nice, I think,
لن يكون جميلاً , أعتقد ,
when the blue-haired lady in the doctor's waiting room
عندما تتواجد سيدة مزرقة الشعر في غرفة انتظار الطبيب
bends over the magazine table
تقلب المجلة على الطاولة
and farts, just a little,
وضرطت , قليلا فقط ,
and violently blushes.
وخجلت بقوة
Wouldn't it be nice if intestinal gas
ألن يكون جميلا لو أن تلك الغازات المعوية
came embodied in visible clouds,
تجسدت في غيمة مرئية
so she could see that her really quite inoffensive pop
لترى صاحبة تلك الـ "بوب" الغير مؤذية
had only barely grazed my face
انها لم تخدش سوى وجهي
before it drifted away.
قبل أن تنجرف بعيدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Besides, for this to have happened now
عدا , اذا ماحدث هذا الان
is a nice coincidence. Because not an hour ago,
سيكون مصادفة لطيفة , فقبل ساعة من الان
while we were on our walk,
بينما كنا نمشي
my dog was startled by a backfire
فاجأني كلبي بالنتائج العكسية
and jumped straight up like a horse bucking.
ليقفز للأعلى كالحصان
And that brought back to me the stable
والذي أعاد لي ذكريات الاسطبل
I worked on weekends when I was 12,
كنت أعمل في العطل الأسبوعية عندما كنت في الـ12,
and a splendid piebald stallion,
وعلى ظهر حصان رائع أبقع,
who whenever he was mounted would buck just like that,
الذي كان أينما صعد يثب هكذا,
though more hugely of course,
وان كان بشكل أكبر بطبيعة الحال
enormous, gleaming, resplendent.
شاسع , براق , لامع
And the woman, her face abashedly buried
والمرأة , دفنت وجهها خزيا
in her "Elle" now, reminded me --
في ماهيتها الان , تذكرني --
I'd forgotten that not the least part of my awe
فيما كدت انسى بأن جزءاً من رعبي
consisted of the fact that with every jump he took
تمثل في أن كل قفزة قفزها
the horse would powerfully fart.
كان الحصان يضرط بقوة
Phwap! Phwap! Phwap!
فواب! فواب! فواب!
Something never mentioned
شيء لم يذكر أبدا
in the dozens of books about horses
في عشرات الكتب التي تحدثت عن الخيول
and their riders I devoured in those days.
وفرسانها التي التهمتها في تلك الايام
All that savage grandeur,
كل تلك العظمة الوحشية ,
the steely glinting hooves,
الحوافر الفولاذية ذات الوميض,
the eruptions driven from the creature's mighty innards,
الانفجارات مدفوعة من الاحشاء القوية لذاك المخلوق
breath stopped, heart stopped, nostrils madly flared,
الصدر لأعلى , قلب متوقف , خياشيم متوهجة بجنون
I didn't know if I wanted to break him, or be him.
لم أميز هل أردت أن أوقفه أو أن أكون هو
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is called "Thirst."
هذه أسميتها "ظمأ"
Many -- most of my poems actually
الكثير -- اغلب قصائدي حقيقة
are urban poems. I happen to be reading a bunch that aren't.
قصائد حضرية . سأحاول أن أقرأ باقة منها
"Thirst."
"ظمأ"
Here was my relation with the woman who lived all last autumn and winter,
هنا كانت علاقاتي مع المرأة التي عاشت أواخر الخريف والشتاء
day and night, on a bench
ليلا ونهارا على مقعد
in the 103rd Street subway station,
في محطة نفق الشارع 103
until finally one day she vanished.
حتى اختفت في احدى الايام
We regarded each other, scrutinized one another.
نظرنا واحدنا للآخر , تفحصنا بعضنا البعض بدقة
Me shyly, obliquely, trying not to be furtive.
أنا باستحياء, بشكل غير مباشر, أحاول أن لا أكون ماكرا
She boldly, unblinkingly, even pugnaciously,
هي بجرأة, بشكل لايرف, بمشاكسة حتى
wrathfully even, when her bottle was empty.
بغضب حتى عندما فرغت قنينتها
I was frightened of her. I felt like a child.
كنت مرعوبا منها .شعرت وكأني طفل
I was afraid some repressed part of myself
كنت خائفا بعض الجزء المكبوت من نفسي
would go out of control, and I'd be forever entrapped
سيخرج عن السيطرة, وسأصبح محاصرا للأبد
in the shocking seethe of her stench.
بصدمة هيجان رائحتها الكريهة
Not excrement merely, not merely surface
ليس مجرد غائط ولا سطحي بكل بساطة
and orifice going unwashed,
كثقب لتسده الأوساخ
rediffusion of rum,
ينتشر كشراب مسكر,
there was will in it,
كان هناك ارادة في ذلك,
and intention, power and purpose --
وعزم,قوة وقصد,
a social, ethical rage and rebellion --
الحياة الاجتماعية والاخلاقية الغضب والتمرد
despair too, though, grief, loss.
اختفت أيضا,على الرغم من الحزن والخسارة
Sometimes I'd think I should take her home with me,
أحيانا أفكر بأن علي أخذها الى المنزل معي
bathe her, comfort her, dress her.
تحميمها, تريحها والباسها
She wouldn't have wanted me to, I would think.
هي لاترد مني ذلك , فكرت
Instead, I'd step into my train.
بدلا من ذلك ,سأخطو الى قطاري
How rich I would think, is the lexicon
كم هو غني , المعجم
of our self-absolving.
المختص بتبرئة ذاتنا
How enduring, our bland fatal assurance
كم تتحمل شجاعتنا القاتلة الودودة
that reflection is righteousness being accomplished.
هذا الانعكاس له أحقية التمام
The dance of our glances,
رقص لمحاتنا,
the clash, pulling each other through
اشتباك , سحب بعضهم البعض من خلال
our perceptual punctures,
ثقوب ادراكنا
then holocaust, holocaust,
ثم محرقة , محرقة
host on host of ill, injured presences,
ضيف على حشد من المرضى ,جرح الوجود
squandered, consumed.
بعثر , استهلك,
Her vigil somewhere I know continues.
احتجاجها في مكان ما وأنا أعلم أنه مازال مستمرا
Her occupancy, her absolute, faithful attendance.
انشغالها ,استبدادها , حضورها المخلص
The dance of our glances, challenge, abdication,
رقص لمحاتنا ,تحدي, تنازل
effacement, the perfume of our consternation.
عفو , وعطر من خوفنا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is a newer poem, a brand new poem.
هذه أحدث قصيدة,
The title is "This Happened."
عنوانها " هذا ماحدث "
A student, a young woman
طالبة , شابة
in a fourth-floor hallway of her lycee,
في مدخل الطابق الرابع من مدرستها الثانوية
perched on the ledge of an open window
تجلس على حافة نافذة مفتوحة
chatting with friends between classes;
تتحدث مع أصدقاء بين الحصص
a teacher passes and chides her,
يمر المدرس ويوبخها ,
"Be careful, you might fall,"
"انتبهي , قد تسقطين "
almost banteringly chides her,
بمزاح تقريبا وبخها,
"You might fall,"
"قد تسقطين"
and the young woman, 18, a girl really,
والشابة , بعمر الثامنة عشر, أنثى حقا
though she wouldn't think that,
بالرغم من عدم إعتقادها ذلك
as brilliant as she is, first in her class,
لامعة كما هي دائما , الآولى في صفها
and "Beautiful, too," she's often told,
و "جميلة أيضا ,"كثيرا مايقال لها ذلك ,
smiles back, and leans into the open window,
ترد ألابتسامات , وتميل الى الشباك المفتوح ,
which wouldn't even be open if it were winter --
الذي لايفتح اذا كان الفصل شتاء ,
if it were winter someone would have closed it ("Close it!") --
اذا كان شتاء هناك شخصا سيقوم بأغلاقه ( "أغلقيه" )
leans into the window, farther, still smiling,
تميل الى الشباك , ابعد , مازلت تبتسم ,
farther and farther, though it takes less time
أبعد وأبعد , بالرغم من أخذها وقتا أقل
than this, really an instant, and lets herself fall.
أكثر من هذا , حقيقة في لحظة , جعلت نفسها تسقط .
Herself fall.
أوقعت نفسها .
A casual impulse, a fancy,
دفعة عصرية ,نزوة
never thought of until now, hardly thought of even now ...
لم تفكر في مابعد الان , من الصعب حتى أن تفكر في الان
No, more than impulse or fancy,
لا , أكثر من اندفاع نزوة
the girl knows what she's doing,
الفتاة تعلم ماهي مقدمة عليه
the girl means something,
الفتاة تعني شيئا
the girl means to mean,
الفتاة عنت أن تعني
because it occurs to her in that instant,
لأنه يحدث لها في تلك اللحظة
that beautiful or not, bright yes or no,
أهو جميل أم لا, لامع أم لا
she's not who she is,
هي لم تعلم من هي
she's not the person she is,
هي ليست الشخص التي هي عليه
and the reason, she suddenly knows,
والسبب بأنها فجأة علمت
is that there's been so much premeditation
هو انه هناك الكثير من التعمد
where she is, so much plotting and planning,
اين هي , هناك الكثير من التآمر والخطط
there's hardly a person where she is,
لايكاد ان يوجد انسان حيث تعيش
or if there is, it's not her, or not wholly her,
وان كان هناك , هو ليس هنا , او ليس هنا كليا
it's a self inhabited, lived in by her,
انها الذات المأهولة , المسكونة بها
and seemingly even as she thinks it
وعلى مايبدو حتى عندما تعتقد هي
she knows what's been missing:
انها تعلم ماالمنقوص
grace,
الصبر
not premeditation but grace,
ليس التعمد بل الرحمة
a kind of being in the world spontaneously,
نوع من التواجد في الحياة بعفوية,
with grace.
بصبر
Weightfully upon me was the world.
كان العالم ثقل على كاهلي
Weightfully this self which graced the world
ثقل هي النفس التي زينت العالم
yet never wholly itself.
رغم ذلك هي نفس كلية
Weightfully this self which weighed upon me,
ثقل هي النفس المفروضة علي
the release from which is what I desire
الافراج عنها هو مااشتهي
and what I achieve.
وهو ماأنجزته
And the girl remembers, in this infinite instant
تذكرت الفتاة , في هذه اللحظة اللانهائية
already now so many times divided,
الان بالفعل مضى كثير من الوقت
the sadness she felt once,
الحزن شعرت به مرة
hardly knowing she felt it,
من الصعب إدراك انها شعرت به
to merely inhabit herself.
لمجرد أنه سكن روحها
Yes, the girl falls, absurd to fall,
نعم , سقطت الفتاة, من السخف أن تسقط
even the earth with its compulsion
حتى الارض مع إلزامها
to take unto itself all that falls
لتلتقط كل مايسقط
must know that falling is absurd,
كانت تعلم بأن السقوط ماهو الا سخف
yet the girl falling isn't myself,
ومع ذلك سقوط الفتاة ليس سقوطي
or she is myself,
او ربما هي أنا
but a self I took of my own volition unto myself.
لكن النفس التي اخدتها بمحض ارادتي الى نفسي
Forever. With grace.
للابد , بصبر
This happened.
هذا ماحدث
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'll read just one more. I don't usually say that.
سأقرأ مرة واحدة بعد. لاأقول هذا بالعادة
I like to just end.
أرغب فقط في الختام
But I'm afraid that Ricky will come out here
لكنني أخاف أن ريكي سيصعد الى هنا
and shake his fist at me.
وسيهز يده لي
This is called "Old Man," appropriately enough.
هذه تسمى " الرجل العجوز" ملائمة بما فيه الكفاية
"Special: big tits,"
خاصة. الاثداء الكبيرة
Says the advertisement for a soft-core magazine
قال الاعلان لمجلة خلاعية
on our neighborhood newsstand.
على كشك بيع صحف حينا
But forget her breasts.
لكن لتنسى ثدييها
A lush, fresh-lipped blond,
خصب, إضاءة حية شقراء
skin glowing gold, sprawls there,
بشرة ذهبية لامعة , تنتشر هناك
resplendent.
بتألق
60 nearly, yet these hardly tangible,
تقارب الـ60, رغم ذلك تظهر بالكاد ملموسة
hardly better than harlots, can still stir me.
بالكاد أفضل من العاهرات, مازالت قادرة على إثارتي
Maybe a coming of age in the
ربما هي قادمة من عصور
American sensual darkness,
الظلام الحسي الأمريكي
never seeing an unsmudged nipple,
لم أرى حلمة ملطخة,
an uncensored vagina,
ومهبل غير خاضع للرقابة,
has left me forever infected
لتتركني فاسدا للأبد
with an unquenchable lust of the eye.
مع رغبة جامحة للعين
Always that erotic murmur,
تلك الدندنة الجنسية الدائمة,
I'm hardly myself
بالكاد أجد نفسي
if I'm not in a state of incipient desire.
ان لم أكن في حالة الرغبة الأولية
God knows though,
يعلم الله بالرغم
there are worse twists your obsessions can take.
من وجود أسوأ المنعطفات التي قد تسكلها هواجسك
Last year in Israel, a young ultra-orthodox Rabbi
في العام الماضي في اسرائيل, من الشباب المتطرف الحاخام الارثودكسي
guiding some teenage girls through the Shrine of the Shoah
قاد مجموعة من المراهقات خلال ضريح المحرقة
forbade them to look in one room.
مانعا إياهن من النظر الى غرفة واحدة
Because there were images in it he said were licentious.
لأنه هناك صور على حد قوله خليعة
The display was a photo. Men and women stripped naked,
المعروض كان صورة , رجال ونساء مجردين من الملابس
some trying to cover their genitals,
البعض يحاول تغطية أعضائهم التناسلية
others too frightened to bother,
والاخرين مرتعبون من المضايقة
lined up in snow
مصطفين ببرود
waiting to be shot and thrown into a ditch.
منتظرين اطلاق النار والقائهم في حفرة
The girls, to my horror,
الفتيات , الى رعبي
averted their gaze.
اشاحوا ببصرهم
What carnal mistrust had their teacher taught them.
اي سوء ظن جسدي علمهم معلمهم
Even that though. Another confession:
حتى أنه على الرغم من اعتراف آخر
Once in a book on pre-war Poland,
مرة في احدى الكتب ماقبل الحرب البولندية
a studio portrait, an absolute angel,
صورة الاستديو , ملاك مطلق
an absolute angel with tormented, tormenting eyes.
ملاك مطلق بعيون معذبة
I kept finding myself at her page.
وجدت نفسي بصفحتها
That she died in the camps made her --
تلك التي توفت في معسكرات جعلتها--
I didn't dare wonder why --
لم أكن أجرؤ على التساؤل لماذا --
more present, more precious.
أكثر حضورا, أكثر قيمة
Died in the camps, that too people --
ماتت في المخيم , كأغلب الناس هناك --
or Jews anyway --
او اليهود --
kept from their children back then.
ابعدوا عن أطفالهم اذن
But it was like sex, you didn't have to be told.
لكنه كالجنس , ليس عليك الحديث فيه
Sex and death, how close they can seem.
الجنس والموت,كم يبدوان قريبان
So constantly conscious now of death moving towards me,
بخطوات واثقة يخطو الموت نحوي
sometimes I think I confound them.
في بعض الاحيان أعتقد بأني اخلط بينهم
My wife's loveliness almost consumes me.
يستهلكني حسن زوجتي
My passion for her goes beyond reasonable bounds.
وعاطفتي تجاهها تتجاوز حدود المعقول
When we make love, her holding me
عندما نمارس الجنس , تحتجزني
everywhere all around me,
في كل مكان حولي
I'm there and not there.
انا هناك ولست هناك
My mind teems, jumbles of faces, voices, impressions,
وفي ذهني مزيج من الوجوه والاصوات والانطباعات
I live my life over, as though I were drowning.
أعيش حياتي للنهاية وكأنني أغرق
Then I am drowning, in despair
ثم أغرق في اليأس
at having to leave her,
حتى أرحل عنها
this, everything, all,
هذا كل شيء
unbearable, awful.
لايحتمل , مرعب
Still, to be able to die
مازلت قادر على الموت
with no special contrition,
مع عدم وجود ندم خاص
not having been slaughtered, or enslaved.
لم تذبح , ولم تستعبد
And not having to know history's next
وعدم معرفة التاريخ القادم
mad rage or regression,
لتصنع الغضب والارتداد
it might be a relief.
ربما سيكون مريحا
No. Again, no.
لا , مرة أخرى , لا
I don't mean that for a moment.
لم أقصد ذلك للحظة
What I mean is the world holds me so tightly --
ماعنيته بأن العالم جعلني متماكسا جدا--
the good and the bad --
الجيد والسيء --
my own follies and weakness
حماقاتي وضعفي
that even this counterfeit Venus
بل أن هذا التزييف فينوس
with her sham heat, and her bosom probably plumped
مع قيعة خجلها, ونقوش صدرها
with gel, so moves me
بالهلام , قادرة على تحريكي
my breath catches.
التقاط انفاسي
Vamp. Siren. Seductress.
تغوي الرجال , جنية البحر , الغاوية
How much more she reveals
فكم تستطيع ان تكشف
in her glare of ink than she knows.
بوهج حبرها اكثر مما تعرف
How she incarnates
كيف تجسد
our desperate human need for regard,
حاجتنا اللامتناهية للندم
our passion to live in beauty,
شغفنا للعيش بجمال
to be beauty, to be cherished by glances,
لنصبح جميلين , لتعتز باللمحات
if by no more, of something like love,
ان لم يكن أكثر , بشيء يشبه الحب
or love.
او الحب
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)